[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "What is the Sant Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "The Sant Nirankari Mission is a spiritual organization founded in 1929 by Baba Buta Singh Ji Mahraj, that aims to promote universal brotherhood and peace by helping people realize God through the guidance of a living Satguru. The mission has grown into a global organisation under the divine leadership of successive spiritual guides (Sadguru), including Shehanshah Baba Avtar Singh Ji, Baba Gurubachan Singh Ji, Baba Hardev Singh Ji, Mata Savinder Ji, and now Sadguru Mata Sudiksha Ji Mahraj."
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "What is the main message of the Sant Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "The mission teaches that God is formless and omnipresent, and every human being can experience God-realisation in their lifetime through the Satguru’s grace. Its core values are love, humility, unity, and service."
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "Who is the current spiritual head of the Mission?",
    "answer": "As of now, the spiritual head is Satguru Mata Sudiksha Ji Maharaj. Mata Sudiksha Ji has been continuously motivating and guiding the devotees, especially the youth towards a righteous, disciplined and meaningful path. She believes and preaches that Knowing God is the only way to lead a balanced and blissful life."
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "What is meant by “God-Realisation” in this mission?",
    "answer": "God-Realisation means experiencing and becoming aware of the formless God (Nirankar) within and around us. This is made possible by the Satguru during a spiritual revelation (Brahmgyan)."
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "What is the role of the Satguru in the Sant Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "The Satguru is the enlightened master who grants God-knowledge and guides followers on how to live a truthful and spiritual life filled with love, service, and devotion."
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "What are the key practices of the Mission?",
    "answer": "The mission emphasizes three main practices:\n• Sewa (selfless service)\n• Simran (constant remembrance of Nirankar)\n• Satsang (attending spiritual gatherings for growth and unity)"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Does the Sant Nirankari Mission follow a particular religion?",
    "answer": "No. Sant Nirankari Mission is a spiritual ideology which believes God is one formless Nirankar and can be realized with grace of Sadguru. The mission respects all religions. It focuses on spirituality and humanity, encouraging people of all backgrounds to come together in peace."
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "What is the purpose of Satsang in the mission?",
    "answer": "Satsang is a spiritual congregation where followers come together to listen to discourses, sing devotional hymns, and strengthen their connection with God."
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "What social work does the mission do?",
    "answer": "The mission organizes blood donation drives, tree plantation, cleanliness campaigns, disaster relief, health camps, and youth development programs. The Sant Nirankari Charitable Foundation is the social wing of Sant Nirankari Mission."
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "What does “Nirankar” mean?",
    "answer": "“Nirankar” means formless God—the eternal, omnipresent divine power that cannot be seen with physical eyes but can be experienced through divine knowledge (Brahmgyan) granted by the Satguru."
  }
  ,
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "What is Brahmgyan (God-Knowledge)?",
    "answer": "Brahmgyan is the realisation of the formless God that is given directly by the Satguru."
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "How does the Mission help in day-to-day life?",
    "answer": "The teachings help individuals to live a peaceful, ego-free, and balanced life. They encourage forgiveness, self-discipline, positive thinking, and service to others, which improves personal and social life."
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "What role do youth play in the Mission?",
    "answer": "Youth are seen as the future of the Mission and society. Special platforms like Nirankari Youth Symposiums and Sewadal Training are organized to engage youth in spirituality and selfless service."
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "What is Nirankari Sewadal?",
    "answer": "The Sant Nirankari Sewadal (SNSD) is a disciplined group of volunteers of the Sant Nirankari Mission dedicated to the selfless service of the humankind. It was established in 1956 by Baba Avtar Singh Ji and later expanded with the women’s wing by Nirankari Rajmata Ji. Sewadal volunteers tirelessly support the Mission’s spiritual events, social activities, and serve humanity with humility under the guidance of Satguru. Their motto 'Nar sewa, Narayan pooja' reflects their belief in serving God through service to mankind."
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "What is the Nirankari Sant Samagam?",
    "answer": "The Sant Nirankari Samagam is a large gathering of devotees celebrating spiritual enlightenment and oneness. It is a festival of unity, service, and divine knowledge. The presence of the Satguru makes it a sacred experience for devotees, where they reinforce their spiritual understanding and share a strong sense of global brotherhood – ‘Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam’."
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "How can someone join the Sant Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "Anyone can join by attending Satsang gatherings, meeting a Gyan Pracharak, and receiving Brahmgyan from the Satguru’s representative."
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "Does the Mission encourage education and careers?",
    "answer": "Absolutely. The Mission believes in balancing spiritual and worldly responsibilities. It encourages followers to study, work honestly, and succeed in life while staying grounded in values."
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "What is the Sant Nirankari Charitable Foundation (SNCF)?",
    "answer": "The SNCF is the social wing of the Mission established in 2010 to serve society with the motto 'Life gets a meaning, if it is lived for others'. It works across three areas: social responsibility, environmental initiatives, and healthcare programs, guided by the principle of Service with Humility."
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "What are the core values of Sant Nirankari Charitable Foundation (SNCF)?",
    "answer": "The core values are HEAL, ENRICH, and EMPOWER:\n1. HEAL – Improving access to healthcare and promoting environmental conservation.\n2. ENRICH – Supporting education through schools, libraries, training centers, etc.\n3. EMPOWER – Encouraging self-reliance through youth/women empowerment programs, disaster relief, and support for the elderly and disabled."
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "What are the spiritual texts of the Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "The two key spiritual texts of the Mission are Sampurna Avtar Bani and Sampurna Hardev Bani. These texts guide individuals on the path of righteousness and universal brotherhood, focusing on the common spiritual teachings found in all holy scriptures."
  }
  ,
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "What is Sampurna Avtar Bani?",
    "answer": "Scripted and blessed by Baba Avtar Singh Ji, Sampurna Avtar Bani is a collection of 376 pious verses that gently take a seeker from the state of oblivion, illusion and fear to the most coveted identity of being One with One. Originally written in Punjabi, it has been translated into many regional and international languages including English, Hindi, Marathi, Gujarati, Bengali, etc."
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "What is Sampurna Hardev Bani?",
    "answer": "A gift of Baba Hardev Singh Ji to humanity, the Sampurna Hardev Bani is a collection of 301 sacred verses originally scripted in Hindi. It deals with contemporary issues affecting the human psyche and captures the essence of Baba Ji’s teachings and wisdom in a deeply reflective and relatable manner."
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "What are the Magazines & Literature of Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "‘Ek Nazar’, ‘Sant Nirankari’, and ‘Hansti Duniya’ are regular magazines of the Mission published in many languages. The Nirankari Publication has produced numerous books that share the Mission’s history, ideology, and activities, while also addressing social and spiritual topics in depth."
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "What are the five tenets/five principles/five pledges of Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "The five pledges are:\n1. Treat body, mind, and possessions as God's gifts, without ego.\n2. Avoid ego based on caste, creed, color, or race.\n3. Do not hate others for their food habits, dress, or lifestyle.\n4. Fulfill family and social responsibilities; do not become a recluse.\n5. Do not share God-Knowledge without the consent of the Satguru."
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "What are the seven stars in Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "The 'Seven Stars' refers to the first Executive Committee of the Sant Nirankari Mandal formed in 1948. These devoted members included:\n1. President – Shri Labh Singh Ji\n2. Vice-President – Dr. Des Raj Ji\n3. Secretary – Shri Ram Saran Ji\n4. Vice-Secretary – Babu Mahadev Singh Ji\n5. Publication In-charge – Shri Santokh Singh Ji\n6. Treasurer – Shri Jugal Kishore Ji (Kabir Ji)\n7. Langar In-charge – Shri Bhagat Ramchandar Ji\nThey were known for their deep devotion and service to the Mission."
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "What is being Nirankari or what is the meaning of Nirankari?",
    "answer": "Being a Nirankari means being spiritually awakened through the grace of the Satguru, recognizing and connecting with the formless, omnipresent God (Nirankar). A Nirankari lives by remembering God through Simran and God-Knowledge (Gyan). The three lines of Simran are:\n“Tu Hi Nirankar” (Only YOU are the Formless Almighty God)\n“Main Teri Sharan Haan” (I completely surrender unto YOU)\n“Mainu Baksh Lo” (Forgive all my sins)"
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "What is the Simran (Remembrance of Almighty God) in Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "“Tu Hi Nirankar” (Only YOU are the Formless Almighty God)\n“Main Teri Sharan Haan” (I completely surrender unto YOU)\n“Mainu Baksh Lo” (Forgive all my sins)"
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "What are the different Samagams in Nirankari Mission?",
    "answer": "Annual Sant Samagam, Bhakti Parv Samagam, Manav Ekta Diwas, Samarpan Diwas, Mukti Parv, and Regional Samagams."
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "Tell me something about Annual Sant Samagam?",
    "answer": "Started in 1948 by Baba Avtar Singh Ji, the Annual Nirankari Sant Samagam now attracts around a million devotees globally. Currently held in Samalkha, Haryana, it includes Sewa activities, huge congregations, cultural programs, a Sewadal rally, Shobha Yatra, Guru Vandana, and community kitchen facilities. The Samagam celebrates spiritual oneness, diversity, and service."
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "What is Bhakti Parv Samagam?",
    "answer": "Held in the second week of January every year, Bhakti Parv Samagam celebrates devotion and gratitude toward Nirankar. It takes place globally, with the main gathering near Sarovar Complex, New Delhi. Devotees reflect on the teachings of saints and sages through speeches, songs, and poems. Many saints also take a dip in the sacred Nirankari Sarovar."
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "What is Manav Ekta Diwas, when is it observed?",
    "answer": "Observed on 24th April, Manav Ekta Diwas honors the martyrdom of Baba Gurbachan Singh Ji, who sacrificed his life for humanity. The day promotes human unity and features mass blood donations across the world. The sacrifice of Chacha Pratap Singh Ji is also remembered. The message is: 'Blood should flow in veins and not in drains.'"
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "What is Samarpan Diwas?",
    "answer": "Observed on 13th May, Samarpan Diwas honors the life and teachings of Baba Hardev Singh Ji Maharaj, who embodied divine principles of love, humility, and service. His global spiritual work continues to inspire. The day also pays tribute to Rev. Avneet Setya Ji, who passed away in the same tragic accident in 2016."
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "What is Mukti Parv Diwas?",
    "answer": "Mukti Parv, observed on 15th August, emphasizes the soul’s liberation and pays homage to departed saints like Shahenshah Baba Avtar Singh Ji, Mata Budhwanti Ji, Baba Gurbachan Singh Ji, and others. It aligns with India's Independence Day, symbolizing spiritual freedom. It reinforces the Mission’s belief in salvation through Satguru’s grace."
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "What is Regional Samagam?",
    "answer": "Regional Samagams are spiritual gatherings held in various parts of India, such as Maharashtra, Bihar, Gujarat, etc. These reflect the Mission’s universal values and promote unity in diversity. Despite different languages and cultures, the Samagams reflect oneness with Nirankar and the Satguru's teachings."
  }
]
